<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Data Artificer and code:Breaker</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Data Artificer and code:Breaker</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 09:17:05 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://n1o.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Graph Neural Networks meet Large Language Models</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/graph-neural-networks-meet-large-language-models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 09:17:05 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/graph-neural-networks-meet-large-language-models/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading I am a huge fan of Graph Neural Networks (GNNs), and I am (a bit less) a fan of Large Language Models (LLMs), however they are hard to ignore. Both have different strengths, while GNNs excel when it comes to problems that have an inherent structure, LLMs thrive in cases where we treat everything as a sequence of tokens (maybe Bytes in the future). A natural question arises, what if we can combine these two?</description></item><item><title>Hymba, a new breed of SSM-Attention Hybrids</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/hymba-new-ssm-att-hybrid-breed/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 07:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/hymba-new-ssm-att-hybrid-breed/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading State space models are really close to my heart, I even have a dedicated page about them. But when it comes to Language Models they lack some performance and that gave rise to SSM-Attention Hybrids. Until now it was conventional that in hybrid layers you sequentially combine Mamba(2) with Attention layers. Nvidia introduced Hymba - this paper changes the game by using Attention and Mamba2 in the same layer, each of them processing the same input tokens.</description></item><item><title>Transform any LLMs to a powerful Encoder</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/from-llms-to-sentence-embeddings/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 09:00:33 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/from-llms-to-sentence-embeddings/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading In the last two years there has been a surge of Large Language Models. This is understandable, since LLMs are amazing at generating text, and a lot of things can be viewed as text. However, generation is not always all we need - sometimes we want to have semantically rich representations. In general, LLMs are not the best tool to get semantically rich representations, and even today models like BERT are used to achieve state of the art text embeddings.</description></item><item><title>2025 Year of Zig</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/2025-yearl-of-zig/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 08:31:40 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/2025-yearl-of-zig/</guid><description>Intro Link to heading Programming languages come and go and during my 20 years of coding I have used many of them to at least some degree (more than just hello world). Thanks to ThePrimeagen I decided to take Zig for a spin. And boy I really like it! Just look at the mascot:
Come on, a crocodile with a jetpack? How cool is that?
Why Zig Link to heading Sure I would not invest a lot of time into anything that a full time YouTuber recommends.</description></item><item><title>Distilling State Space Models from Transformers</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/distilling-ssm-from-transformers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 10:12:27 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/distilling-ssm-from-transformers/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading It is notoriously expensive to train a Language Model from scratch, making independent research impossible and trying out new architectures extremely risky. Because of these costs, Transformer++ models like LLaMa, based on Rotary Embedding, SwiGLU, MLP, RMSNorm, without linear bias, sometimes with grouped query attention and/or sliding window attention, are the de facto standard, not because they are the best, but because they are proven to work!</description></item><item><title>Illusion of State in SSMs like Mamba</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/ssm-the-illusion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 10:52:09 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/ssm-the-illusion/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading Last time we looked into the weak points of State Space Models (Mamba, Mamba2), especially when compared with Attention-Based models (LLama, GPT-like). They lack in terms of in-context learning. To alleviate this, we focused on SSM-Transformer Hybrids and introduced multiple models that do this differently. Here we look into the expressivity of State Space Models from two formal perspectives. The first is from the perspective of Circuit complexity and later from the perspective of Formal Languages.</description></item><item><title>Mamba(2) and Transformer Hybrids: An Overview</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/ssm-transformer-hybrids-guide/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 11:26:25 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/ssm-transformer-hybrids-guide/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading We have already looked into Mamba and Mamba2. In terms of efficiency, with their linear complexity and the absence of Key-Value cache, they are a significant improvement over Attention-based models in terms of throughput and memory usage. However, not everything is perfect. Transformers have a certain advantage when it comes to in-context learning. In-context learning is the ability to adapt the model without retraining it. This is done by providing relevant (or not) context to the model in the form of a prompt.</description></item><item><title>Awesome SSM</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/awesome-ssm/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 10:39:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/awesome-ssm/</guid><description>This series will cover a bunch of posts about State Space Models, their extensions and applications.
Basics Link to heading Mamba, Mamba2 Bidirectional Link to heading Hydra Attention Hybrids Link to heading SSM-Transformer Hybrids covers: An Empirical Study of Mamba-based Language Models SAMBA Simple Hybrid State Space Models for Efficient Unlimited Context Language Modeling Jamba A Hybrid Transformer-Mamba Language Model Jamba 1.5 Hybrid Transformer-Mamba Models at Scale Zamba A Compact 7B SSM Hybrid Model Zamba2-small Zamba2-mini Hymba Hymba: A Hybrid-head Architecture for Small Language Models instead of having Attention and Mamba running in alternating layers we run them in parallel in the same layer Theory and Limitations Link to heading Illusion of State in SSMs like Mamba covers: The Expressive Capacity of State Space Models: A Formal Language Perspective The Illusion of State in State-Space Models With Graphs Link to heading Graph Mamba: Towards Learning on Graphs with State Space Models we leverage SSMs an alternative to Message Passing in Graph Neural Networks Distillation Link to heading Hohawk and Mamba in the Llama covers:</description></item><item><title>Hydra a Double Headed Mamba</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/hydra-a-double-headed-mamba/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 11:53:51 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/hydra-a-double-headed-mamba/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading State Space Models are awesome, models like Mamba and Mamba2 boast unparalleled performance especially when it comes to long sequences. The only downside is that they are causal, which means they model one token at a time, looking only at past tokens. Bidirectional models like Bert, CodeBERT and GraphCodeBERT have been shown to excel when it comes to code understanding. One way to put it is that by looking into the past and the future simultaneously we can get a better understanding of what is happening.</description></item><item><title>From Mamba to Mamba-2</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/from-mamba-to-mamba2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 09:57:32 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/from-mamba-to-mamba2/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading This is not my first gig where I write about State Space Models. I already mentioned them here and here. Now what is the deal with this Mamba(2) thing? They are proving to be an alternative to the strong Transformer++ architecture (Transformer++ models like LLaMa are based on Rotary Embedding, SwiGLU, MLP, RMSNorm, without linear bias, sometimes with grouped query attention and/or sliding window attention). Hold on, if this Transformer++ models work well, why do we need altneratives?</description></item><item><title>Butterflies, Monarchs, Hyenas, and Lightning Fast BERT</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/butterflies-monarchs-hyenas-and-lightning-fast-bert/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 13:36:49 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/butterflies-monarchs-hyenas-and-lightning-fast-bert/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading I have been working on a project of creating my own Large Language Model, as I am huge fan of T5, or to be more concrete I recognize the added value of having an Encoder-Decoder architecture. The biggest challenge, at least in my opinion, in training an LLM is the sheer computational costs required to do so. I was originally planning to take the Encoder introduced by ColT5 but than I came across of M2 BERT and suddenly I went down the rabbit hole of Structured Matrices, Butterflies, Monarch and Hyeans.</description></item><item><title>BinT5 and HexT5 or T5 and Binary Reverse Engineering</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/t5-and-reverse-engineering/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2024 14:07:17 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/t5-and-reverse-engineering/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading For a while now I have a new passion and that is binary reverse engineering and vulnerability exploitation. This interest has led me to create CodeBreakers a platform dedicated to applying machine learning to reverse engineering, vulnerability detection, exploitation, and other cybersecurity-related applications.
I found two notable research papers where T5 has been applied to reverse engineering are BinT5 and HexT5. Before we dive deep into the details of these papers, let&amp;rsquo;s first explore the basics of reverse engineering.</description></item><item><title>CodeT5 and CodeT5+</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/code-t5-plus/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 08:46:43 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/code-t5-plus/</guid><description>Abstract Link to heading In a previous post, T5 the Old New Thing, we briefly touched upon CodeT5 and CodeT5+. Now, we aim to dive deeper into these topics.
I have previously explored CodeBERT and GraphCodeBERT. These models, based on BERT and RoBERTa architectures, excel at code understanding and retrieval tasks. However, they fall short when it comes to code generation tasks. It&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that these models share a common theme: they utilize unique pretraining objectives tailored specifically for source code.</description></item><item><title>Awesome T5</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/awesome-t5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 17:31:29 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/awesome-t5/</guid><description>Here is a bunch of my posts about a super cool model called T5 its extensions and applications.
Basics Link to heading T5, FLAN-T5, UL2 LongT5, CoLT5 Coding T5 Link to heading CodeT5, CodeT5+ AST-T5 (Coming Soon) CodeFusion (Commit Soon) there is a bit of confusion about this research paper, there are some citation issues, and the overall reviews are not that great, however it still sounds like an interesting research direction, and will cover it but it may be a short one Cyber Security Link to heading LENS (Coming Soon) BinT5, HexT5 or &amp;ldquo;How is T5 used for Binary Reverse Engineering&amp;rdquo; With Graphs Link to heading Graph Neural Prompting (Coming Soon)</description></item><item><title>Longer Context for T5</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/longer-context-for-t5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 14:10:36 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/longer-context-for-t5/</guid><description>Why does T5 need a longer context? Link to heading In my previous post T5 the Old New Thing we already explored why T5 is awesome. But one downside is its limited context length of 512 tokens. However, it does have a limitation - its context length is restricted to 512 tokens. This can&amp;rsquo;t be directly compared to the context length of a decoder-only model, as T5 is an encoder-decoder model.</description></item><item><title>T5 the Old New Thing</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/t5-the-old-new-thing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 12:58:32 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/t5-the-old-new-thing/</guid><description>Why T5 Link to heading A couple of weeks ago I run into the following paper Tiny Titans. It compares multiple smallish (up to 1B parameters) open source LLMs with bigger proprietary ones on meeting summarization. TLDR; the small models tend to perform worse in zero-shot setting as well after fine-tunnig than big ones. Except for FLAN-T5-Large which after finetuning performs way beyond its league, beating even the biggest proprietary models (GPT-3.</description></item><item><title>Nixos for Hobby Project</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/nixos-for-hobby-project/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2023 13:09:10 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/nixos-for-hobby-project/</guid><description>Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve embarked on a side project: CodeBreakers. It&amp;rsquo;s nothing too fancy, just a website where I plan to release videos and articles about my latest passions—Reverse Engineering and Binary Exploitation.
Creating a website isn&amp;rsquo;t all that complex, and I&amp;rsquo;ve done it a couple of times before. The main challenge was deciding where and how to host it. Initially, I considered using Fly ((which is a fantastic PaaS product with many built-in features), but ultimately, I opted for Hetzner and rented a virtual server.</description></item><item><title>Paper overview: Hungry Hungry Hippos: Towards Language Modeling with State Space Models</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/hungry-hungry-hippos/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 09:39:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/hungry-hungry-hippos/</guid><description>High level overview Link to heading By combining State Space Models (SSMs) with Attention, we get a model that generates text more efficiently, with a speed increase of approximately 1.6 times. Additionally, this approach requires less paremters, enabling the development of larger models on existing hardware.
Language modeling requirements Link to heading The Transformer architecture, which forms the basis of ChatGPT, is riding high on the hype train due to its impressive performance.</description></item><item><title>Paper overview: Continuous-Time Modeling of Counterfactual Outcomes Using Neural Controlled Differential Equations</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/continuous-time-modeling-of-counterfatual-outcomes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 17:37:36 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/continuous-time-modeling-of-counterfatual-outcomes/</guid><description>The problem it solves Link to heading Imagine you have an irregullary sampled time series, where at various time points we perform interventions. These interventions may influence the dynamics of the timeseries. The question we want to answer is:
If I perform a hypothetical sequence of interventions how will my time series evolve?
An example and some details Link to heading Example Link to heading As a medical doctor in a hospital, if a patient has a high fever and is at risk of dying, a common practice is to measure their levels of C-reactive protein (CRP) to determine if they need antibiotics.</description></item><item><title>Hierarchical Probabilistic Matrix Factorization</title><link>https://n1o.github.io/posts/pooled_matrix_factorization/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 10:19:42 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/posts/pooled_matrix_factorization/</guid><description>Probabilistic Matrix factorization is a simple but useful model for matrix imputation. The main idea is to decompose a tall and wide matrix into a product of two matrices, one tall and thin and one short and wide.
$$ R_{n\times m} = U_{m \times d} \cdot V_{d \times n} $$
If you are a Bayesian, you can express this model as:
$$ R_{ij} \sim \mathcal{N}(u_i \cdot v_j^T, \sigma) $$ $$ u_i \sim \mathcal{N}(\mu_u, \Sigma_u) $$ $$ v_j \sim \mathcal{N}(\mu_v, \Sigma_v) $$</description></item><item><title/><link>https://n1o.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/about/</guid><description>About Link to heading I&amp;rsquo;m Marek Barak, I started my journey into computer science when I was 15 by coding in C++, without having access to the internet and in good old fashioned Bloodshed C++. Since then nearly 20 years have passed, and I managed to get a Master degree in Computer Science and Statistics from the University of Economics in Bratislava. I had the opportunity to do machine learning and build distributed systems for early to mid stage startups.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://n1o.github.io/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/contact/</guid><description>Contact Link to heading Feel free to contact me via email mrk.barak@gmail.com or socials.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://n1o.github.io/projects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://n1o.github.io/projects/</guid><description>Projects Link to heading Study notes Link to heading This is my compilation of notes from various subjects. This is work in progress, where I continuously migrate, rewrite, simplify the notes I have. During the years I wrote thousands of pages worth of notes, not always concise. Right now I prefer taking notes that are somewhat similar to the Zettelkasten method. Thus keeping them short, easy to follow, covering at most a single subject.</description></item></channel></rss>